Petworth Women's Club 052
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Petworth Women's Club Collection
1914-1964
1915-1955
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Petworth Women's Club
052
3.5 Linear feet
10 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Programs, 1920-1939; 1964 (.50 linear ft.): The series consists primarily of programs for the club's annual banquets. It also contains programs of other events including the Allegiance Luncheon of the Women's National Committee for Law Enforcement in 1926, the Children's Patriotic Parade…List of Entries for 1924, and the Club's golden anniversary program in 1964. Items are arranged chronologically. Series 2: Yearbooks, 1921-1959 (.50 linear ft.): The series contains the club's yearbooks. Each yearbook includes a list of officers, section chairman and members, standing and special committees, members, meetings, and a report from the President. Yearbooks are arranged chronologically. Series 3: Sections and Committees, 1915-1933 (.50 linear ft.): The series contains many handwritten and typed meeting minutes and reports of sections/committees. The sections carried out the many charitable and educational activities of the club. Activities included sewing children's garments for orphanages, collecting food and clothes for the poor, offering lectures on women's suffrage and homemaking, conducting poetry readings, book discussions, neighborhood beautification projects, forming a visiting home nurses group, and lobbying for the Petworth schools, a branch library, and less car pollution. Also included in the series are meeting minutes of the Executive Committee of the Club in the early 1920s. The folders are arranged alphabetically by the name of the committee. Series 4: General Files, 1916-1964 (.25 linear ft.): The series contains folders on a variety of topics loosely arranged in chronological order. Much of the series consists of correspondence. It also includes a history of the club prepared in 1964 and minutes from meetings of affiliated organizations such as the D.C. Federation of Women's Clubs and the Public School Administration Association. Series 5: Meeting Minutes, 1914-1964 (.50 linear ft.): The series contains minutes of the meeting of the Club. Series 6: Financial Records, 1915-1954 (l linear ft.): Includes primarily handwritten ledger books containing treasurer reports, member dues, and other club expenditures. Series 7: Clippings, 1924-1949 (.25 linear ft.): The series contains scrapbooks and loose clippings maintained by Club members on the Club's activities and events.
Biographical / Historical
On the evening of July 6, 1914, Mrs. Harriet Hill who lived on Taylor Street called the President of the D.C. Federation of Women's Clubs about organizing a women's club to promote the best interests of Washington, D.C.'s Petworth neighborhood. Eleven women met that evening and officers were elected. Soon after, six sections were formed, including civic, educational, literature, home, philanthropic, music, and art to choose appropriate social, educational, or philanthropic activities for its members. In the early years, membership was limited to women of Petworth, as bounded by Hamilton Street on the North, Rock Creek Church Road on the south, Third Street on the east, and Georgia Avenue to the west. Starting in 1914, monthly business meetings were held in the Petworth School house, then by 1937 at the Petworth Methodist Church. Highlights of club activities included: a campaign led by Mrs. A.C. Norcross for a public library branch in Petworth in the 1920s; a Red Cross Production unit organized during World War II; a visiting nurses group which assisted at the Walter Reed Hospital; and a sewing circle of the Philanthropic section which provided clothes to children at D.C. Village and the Convalescent Hospital for almost 30 years. Charter members included Mrs. Annie Nelson, Mrs. A.C. Norcross, Mrs. Harriet Hill, Mrs. W.F. North, Mrs. Frank H. Schwartz, and Mrs. W. Winklehaus.
Custodial History
Items in this collection were part of the Library's vertical files. To ensure the physical preservation of fragile handwritten documents in the vertical file, in 1999 they were removed and photocopied. Photocopies were returned to the vertical files and the originals are in this collection.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains programs, yearbooks, meeting minutes, reports, membership lists, correspondence, and receipts which document the activities of the Petworth Women's Club.
Neighborhoods; Societies and clubs; Women; Minutes (Records); Organizational Records; Correspondence; Yearbooks; Petworth, Washington, D.C.
- Series 1: Programs, 1920-1939; 1964
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists primarily of programs for the club's annual banquets. It also contains programs of other events including the Allegiance Luncheon of the Woman's National Committee for Law Enforcement in 1926, the Children's Patriotic Parade…List of Entries for 1924, and the Club's golden anniversary program in 1964. Items are arranged chronologically.
  - Annual banquet programs, 1920, 1922-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Children's Patriotic Parade - List of Entries, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allegiance Luncheon - Woman's National Committee for Law Enforcement, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lee Kedrick Lecture Bureau, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Luncheon of the DC Federation of Women's Clubs, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Silver Anniversary Program, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Announcement of officers, 1931, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Invitation to House and Embassy Tour, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Golden Anniversary Luncheon program, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Harvest Dinner and Bazaar, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - An Evening in Old Japan by the Petworth Woman's Club, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Yearbooks, 1921-1959
  The series contains the club's yearbooks. Each yearbook includes a list of officers, section chairman and members, standing and special committees, members, meetings, and a report from the President. Yearbooks are arranged chronologically.
  - Yearbooks, 1921-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Sections and Committees, 1915-1933
  The series contains many handwritten and typed meeting minutes and reports of sections/committees. The sections carried out the many charitable and educational activities where were typical of women's clubs of the period. Activities included sewing children's garments for orphanages; collecting food and clothes for the poor, offering lectures on women's suffrage and homemaking; conducting poetry readings, book discussions, neighborhood beautification projects; forming a visiting home nurses group; and lobbying for the Petworth schools, a branch library, and less car pollution. Also included in the series are meeting minutes of the Executive Committee of the Club in the early 1920s. The folders are arranged alphabetically by the name of the committee.
  - Art Club, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Art Section, 1921-1922, 1925-1926, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Civic Section, 1915-1932 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Educational Section, 1927-1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1920-1922 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Home Section Minutes, 1921-1926, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hospitality Committee, 1920-1927, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Literary Club, 1918-1925 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Literature Section, 1926-1933 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Music Section, 1914-1915, 1922-1926, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Philanthropic Section, 1919-1933 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Visiting Nurses Committee, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Yearbook Committee, 1922-1925 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Committee Reports - General, 1914-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Committee Reports - General, 1914-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Committee Reports - General, 1914-1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Committee Reports - General, 1914-1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Committee Reports - General, 1914-1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series 4: General Files, 1916-1964
  The series contains folders on a variety of topics loosely arranged in chronological order. Much of the series consists of correspondence. It also includes a history of the club prepared in 1964 and minutes from meetings of affiliated organizations such as the D.C. Federation of Women's Clubs and the Public School Administration Association.
  - Presidential Address, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1922 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence re Petworth School, 1916-1922 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1926 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Public School Association Meeting Minutes, 1922-1927 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Officers' reports, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1935 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Corresponding Secretary's reports, 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - President Edith Phelps' papers, 1924-1926 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Financial materials, 1927-1933 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Society Hygiene Society of D.C., 1930s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - D.C. Federation of Women's Clubs meeting minutes, 1931-1933 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Membership lists, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Resolutions, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - WWII misc., 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Club documents, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Awards and certificates, 1958-1964, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Petworth Tribune - Petworth Methodist Church, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - History, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Series 5: Meeting Minutes, 1914-1964
  The series contains minutes of the meeting of the Club.
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1915-1931 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1915-1931 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1915-1931 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1915-1931 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1915-1931 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1915-1931 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes (bound volume), 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1940-1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series 6: Financial Records, 1915-1954
  Includes primarily handwritten ledger books containing treasurer reports, member dues, and other club expenditures.
  - Ledger book, 1915-1926 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Ledger book, 1915-1926 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Ledger book, 1915-1926 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Ledger book, 1915-1926 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Unlabeled folder, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Ledger book, 1930-1948 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Ledger book, 1949-1954 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Ledger book, 1949-1954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Ledger book, 1949-1954 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Ledger book, 1949-1954 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Unlabeled folder, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series 7: Clippings, 1924-1949
  The series contains scrapbooks and loose clippings maintained by Club members on the Club's activities and events.
  - Clippings, 1924-1949 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1924-1949 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Ledger book, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Ledger book, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Ledger book, Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)